<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Urbanism.guide: Development Site – Current Issues</title>
    <link>https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/issues/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Current Issues on Urbanism.guide: Development Site</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	  <atom:link href="https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/issues/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
      
        
      
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Austin: ETOD and Compatibility</title>
      <link>https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/issues/etod_and_compatibility/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/issues/etod_and_compatibility/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-primary&#34; role=&#34;alert&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 class=&#34;alert-heading&#34;&gt;Thanks to our contributors&lt;/h4&gt;

    The majority of the content for this article came from tai_rannosaur on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://discord.gg/eQqxMV5KMq&#34;&gt;AURA Discord&lt;/a&gt;. Contributions like their&amp;rsquo;s make this site possible. If you&amp;rsquo;d like to contribute then check out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zeezephyr/urbanism-guide&#34;&gt;README on the urbanism.guide Github&lt;/a&gt; to find out how.

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;whats-happening&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s Happening?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Austin City Council is &lt;a href=&#34;https://speakupaustin.org/f5610&#34;&gt;proposing three measures&lt;/a&gt; to improve access to housing in Austin by creating more housing; particularly near transit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;equitable-transit-oriented-development-etod&#34;&gt;Equitable Transit Oriented Development (ETOD)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is something called Equitable Transit Oriented Development (ETOD). In plain English, Transit Oriented Development (TOD) means that denser housing could be built within a half mile of the future Project Connect light rail stations. Equitable means that there will be affordability requirements for some of the housing that is constructed within those zones; along with other measures to preserve existing affordable housing and businesses in those areas. Any new building constructed as a result of this proposal can only be done so on land that is already zoned for multifamily or commercial use. It does not affect single family zoned properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under our current land use policies few Austinites can walk or bike to transit. This limited accessibility then leads to less ridership, less transit funding, and worsened service. Transit struggles in low density, car-dependent environments. ETOD turns that vicious cycle into a virtuous cycle where people of all incomes, ages, and backgrounds are able to live near transit; and in this immediate case near the coming light rail of Project Connect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more people living near these new stations, the more people that can conveniently use it in their daily lives. This creates a feedback loop of increasing ridership, funding, and public support for future transit expansion. It also means reduced traffic in the areas along the light rail, reduced environmental pollution, and fewer traffic injuries and deaths. Such zoning changes would also help the city obtain federal grants for Project Connect, thereby ensuring its success.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-secondary&#34; role=&#34;alert&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 class=&#34;alert-heading&#34;&gt;Valid petition&lt;/h4&gt;

    ETOD and other inclusive housing policies have difficulties overcoming a provision of state law known as a &amp;ldquo;valid petition&amp;rdquo; which gives unjust power to land owners to prevent housing. For this reason city policies often avoid changing zoning for single family homes. But this is a battle we can also win. You can learn more about this on &lt;a href=&#34;https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/voting_guide/2024/#the-importance-of-voting&#34;&gt;the 2024 voting guide&lt;/a&gt;.

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;removing-compatibility-restrictions&#34;&gt;Removing &amp;ldquo;Compatibility&amp;rdquo; Restrictions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to ETOD, there is a proposal for changing the &lt;a href=&#34;https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/housing/compatibility_restrictions&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;compatibility&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; rules in the city. This regulation limits the height of buildings near single-family homes. “Near” in this case is not actually a small distance. To be specific, a 60 foot tall apartment building has to be at least 300 feet away from every 35 foot tall single family home in Austin. Compatibility affects housing out to 540 feet, or 1.5 football fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These rules imply that those who live in multifamily homes are incompatible with those who live in single family homes. They are based on old, prejudiced, and discriminatory attitudes that say those living in apartments and condos are not welcome near the majority of the city of Austin; which is predominantly single family homes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to change this, city staff is proposing that those height limits only apply within a 75 foot distance from a single family home. City staff estimates that 63,000 more homes could be built as a result of these policy improvements.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-secondary&#34; role=&#34;alert&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 class=&#34;alert-heading&#34;&gt;Missing housing&lt;/h4&gt;

    According to &lt;a href=&#34;https://services.austintexas.gov/edims/pio/document.cfm?id=414871&#34;&gt;one study&lt;/a&gt; we’re missing out on between 72,000 to 135,000 homes that could be built if &amp;ldquo;compatibility&amp;rdquo; didn&amp;rsquo;t exist. It&amp;rsquo;s not hard to see how these restrictions also limit ETOD development and in doing so restricts publicly funded transit to those lucky or wealthy enough to live in single family homes.

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;home-phase-2&#34;&gt;HOME Phase 2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, HOME phase 2 is being proposed, which would lower the minimum lot size for single family homes, thus making it more affordable to buy a smaller house on a smaller lot. While HOME Phase 1 was a &lt;a href=&#34;https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/wins/2023/#home-options-for-middle-income-empowerment-december-7th&#34;&gt;particularly large victory&lt;/a&gt;, Phase 2 is mostly an add-on rather than any massively impactful policy change. We&amp;rsquo;re happy to see smaller lots but we think it will have a small impact on the availability of housing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;help-get-these-initiatives-passed&#34;&gt;Help Get These Initiatives Passed!&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-primary&#34; role=&#34;alert&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 class=&#34;alert-heading&#34;&gt;You&#39;re not alone&lt;/h4&gt;

    If you have questions or want to be notified about upcoming events then sign up to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://aura-atx.org/subscribe/&#34;&gt;AURA Newsletter&lt;/a&gt; or join the &lt;a href=&#34;https://discord.gg/eQqxMV5KMq&#34;&gt;AURA Discord&lt;/a&gt; and turn on notifications for the #announcements channel. If you prefer another platform then check out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://linktr.ee/aura_atx&#34;&gt;AURA Linktree&lt;/a&gt;.

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These changes will have a massively positive impact on the growth, affordability, and sustainability of our cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be several chances to speak in support of these initiatives at City Hall:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thursday, April 11 (starting at 9 am)&lt;/strong&gt;: Joint Planning Commission and City Council Meeting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tuesday, April 23 (starting at 4 pm): Planning Commission Meeting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tuesday, April 30 (starting at 4 pm): Planning Commission Meeting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thursday, May 16 (starting at 10 am)&lt;/strong&gt;: City Council Meeting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the City Council meetings in bold the sign-ups open the Monday before the meeting; on April 8th and May 13th respectively. Registration closes on Wednesdays at 12PM. You can &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.austintexas.gov/department/public-participation-council-meetings&#34;&gt;learn more about the process on the City Council sign-up page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can sign up to speak either remote (via phone), in person, or simply register your support on the sign-up page without speaking. &lt;strong&gt;Set these sign-up dates in your phone so you don&amp;rsquo;t forget&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When signing up for these meetings you&amp;rsquo;ll be asked to pick an agenda item. These will be listed on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.austintexas.gov/department/public-participation-council-meetings&#34;&gt;sign-up page&lt;/a&gt; but for special meetings like these they&amp;rsquo;re typically the only items on the agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Austin: I-35 Expansion</title>
      <link>https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/issues/i35_expansion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/issues/i35_expansion/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-primary&#34; role=&#34;alert&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 class=&#34;alert-heading&#34;&gt;How to help&lt;/h4&gt;

    Donate to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://rethink35.org/donate&#34;&gt;Rethink35 lawsuit&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zeffy.com/en-US/donation-form/5cac83fd-7f03-4286-b2ba-332fcb635f1b&#34;&gt;become a Rethink35 member&lt;/a&gt; with a recurring donation. &lt;a href=&#34;https://rethink35.org/getinvolved&#34;&gt;Get involved with Rethink35&lt;/a&gt; by volunteering, joining &lt;a href=&#34;https://discord.com/invite/pTvvSgUwFf&#34;&gt;their Discord&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://rethink35.org/events&#34;&gt;attending their events&lt;/a&gt;. They&amp;rsquo;ve also got all the &lt;a href=&#34;https://rethink35.org/getinvolved&#34;&gt;standard social media&lt;/a&gt; that you can follow and share!

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;whats-happening&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s Happening?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TxDOT is set to start construction on a massive I-35 expansion through central Austin in mid-2024. Local groups and elected officials have raised major concerns and opposition to the project, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sept 26, 2023: Travis County Commissioners Court asks TxDOT to comply with air quality and environmental studies for I-35 project; which &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.austinmonitor.com/stories/2023/09/txdot-ignored-i-35-expansion-health-concerns-county-says/&#34;&gt;the county says they did not do&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oct 19, 2023: Austin City Council passed an official resolution asking TxDOT to pause the I-35 project &lt;a href=&#34;https://communityimpact.com/austin/south-central-austin/transportation/2023/10/19/austin-city-council-resolution-to-delay-i-35-project-denied-by-txdot/&#34;&gt;until further environmental review is completed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nov 5, 2023: Over 300 activists &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.statesman.com/picture-gallery/news/local/2023/11/05/hundreds-join-rethink35-rally-in-protest-of-i-35-expansion-project/71467157007/&#34;&gt;attended the “Wider Won’t Work” rally&lt;/a&gt; to oppose I-35 expansion; including U.S. Congressman Greg Casar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TxDOT solicited comments on their draft Environmental Impact Statement. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.restartlonestarraildistrict.org/post/the-public-told-txdot-they-wanted-a-train-instead-of-i-35-expansion-txdot-didn-t-listen&#34;&gt;75% of public comments opposed the expansion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TxDOT has yet to listen to the public, to elected officials, and to common sense that shows &lt;a href=&#34;https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/transportation/highways&#34;&gt;highways have been a fatal and failed experiment&lt;/a&gt; in moving people safely and efficiently around the US.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-dark&#34; role=&#34;alert&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 class=&#34;alert-heading&#34;&gt;Rail is faster&lt;/h4&gt;

    If a train ran along I-35 it could get you from &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/0tRYLxNeNV0&#34;&gt;San Antonio to Austin in 38 minutes&lt;/a&gt;, or from San Antonio to Dallas in 2 hours and 8 minutes.

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;rethink35-lawsuit&#34;&gt;Rethink35 Lawsuit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rethink35 and 16 other plaintiffs have sued TxDOT. The lawsuit alleges:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TxDOT didn&amp;rsquo;t properly study other options such as:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://rethink35.org/proposal&#34;&gt;The Rethink 35 proposal&lt;/a&gt; which involved rerouting the highway and replacing it with a boulevard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://reconnectaustin.com/#home-vis-sec&#34;&gt;The Reconnect Austin vision&lt;/a&gt; which called for the highway being placed underground with a boulevard on top.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TxDOT failed to study several air pollutants and their impacts on the people who live near I-35. This includes particulate matter 2.5 (PM2.5) which puts people at increased risk for asthma and other health conditions. Based on new EPA standards, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kut.org/energy-environment/2024-02-19/austin-area-has-dangerously-high-levels-of-air-pollution-according-to-new-epa-standards&#34;&gt;Austin is already above the safe limit&lt;/a&gt;. TxDOT was &lt;a href=&#34;https://my35capex.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/APPROVED-FEIS-ROD_Appendix-G-Comment-Response-Matrix-from-Public-Hearing-Notice-of-Availability-of-DEIS_2023-08-14.pdf&#34;&gt;aware of this concern&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There was &lt;a href=&#34;https://my35capex.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/APPROVED-FEIS-ROD_Appendix-A-Project-Location-Map_2023-08-14.pdf&#34;&gt;a significant change to the water outfall&lt;/a&gt; that was made after the Draft Environmental Impact Statement was published and so there was no opportunity for public comment. Polluted runoff from the highway will exit into &lt;a href=&#34;https://naturerocksaustin.org/greenspace/colorado-river-preserve&#34;&gt;a wildlife preserve in East Austin&lt;/a&gt;; around US-183 and the Colorado River.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;civil-rights-title-vi-complaint&#34;&gt;Civil Rights (Title VI) Complaint&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rethink35 has also &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/24390031-rethink35-title-vi-complaint-filed&#34;&gt;filed a Title VI civil rights complaint&lt;/a&gt;. The complaint alleges:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I-35 was built to be intentionally discriminatory by replacing East Ave and solidifying a line of segregation between East and West Austin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under Title VI, agencies with a history of prior discrimination have a responsibility to take affirmative action to redress previous injustices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instead, this project exacerbates these very same harmful practices by:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Displacing people from homes and businesses. 86% of the displaced are in Environmental Justice communities (ie. low income, and people of color).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More than doubling the number of lane miles of I-35. Thus widening the barrier between East and West Austin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dumping polluted storm water into a Wildlife Sanctuary in East Austin, continuing a long-standing pattern of moving environmental waste from downtown to East Austin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Worsening air quality, climate change, and increasing summer temperatures, all of which disproportionately burden communities of color.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-primary&#34; role=&#34;alert&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 class=&#34;alert-heading&#34;&gt;Highways as segregation tools&lt;/h4&gt;

    Highway construction and expansion is one of many tools used to systematically segregate our cities. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/housing/housing_segregation&#34;&gt;history of housing segregation&lt;/a&gt; is as brutal as it is banal. These injustices persist to the present day.

&lt;/div&gt;


      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
