<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>An open guide to urbanism – Current Issues</title>
    <link>https://urbanism.guide/austin/issues/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Current Issues on An open guide to urbanism</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	  <atom:link href="https://urbanism.guide/austin/issues/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
      
        
      
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Austin: I-35 Expansion</title>
      <link>https://urbanism.guide/austin/issues/i35_expansion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://urbanism.guide/austin/issues/i35_expansion/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-primary&#34; role=&#34;alert&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 class=&#34;alert-heading&#34;&gt;How to help&lt;/h4&gt;

    Donate to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://rethink35.org/donate&#34;&gt;Rethink35 lawsuit&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zeffy.com/en-US/donation-form/5cac83fd-7f03-4286-b2ba-332fcb635f1b&#34;&gt;become a Rethink35 member&lt;/a&gt; with a recurring donation. &lt;a href=&#34;https://rethink35.org/getinvolved&#34;&gt;Get involved with Rethink35&lt;/a&gt; by volunteering, joining &lt;a href=&#34;https://discord.com/invite/pTvvSgUwFf&#34;&gt;their Discord&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://rethink35.org/events&#34;&gt;attending their events&lt;/a&gt;. They&amp;rsquo;ve also got all the &lt;a href=&#34;https://rethink35.org/getinvolved&#34;&gt;standard social media&lt;/a&gt; that you can follow and share!

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;whats-happening&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s Happening?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TxDOT is set to start construction on a massive I-35 expansion through central Austin in mid-2024. Local groups and elected officials have raised major concerns and opposition to the project, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sept 26, 2023: Travis County Commissioners Court asks TxDOT to comply with air quality and environmental studies for I-35 project; which &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.austinmonitor.com/stories/2023/09/txdot-ignored-i-35-expansion-health-concerns-county-says/&#34;&gt;the county says they did not do&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oct 19, 2023: Austin City Council passed an official resolution asking TxDOT to pause the I-35 project &lt;a href=&#34;https://communityimpact.com/austin/south-central-austin/transportation/2023/10/19/austin-city-council-resolution-to-delay-i-35-project-denied-by-txdot/&#34;&gt;until further environmental review is completed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nov 5, 2023: Over 300 activists &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.statesman.com/picture-gallery/news/local/2023/11/05/hundreds-join-rethink35-rally-in-protest-of-i-35-expansion-project/71467157007/&#34;&gt;attended the “Wider Won’t Work” rally&lt;/a&gt; to oppose I-35 expansion; including U.S. Congressman Greg Casar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TxDOT solicited comments on their draft Environmental Impact Statement. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.restartlonestarraildistrict.org/post/the-public-told-txdot-they-wanted-a-train-instead-of-i-35-expansion-txdot-didn-t-listen&#34;&gt;75% of public comments opposed the expansion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TxDOT has yet to listen to the public, to elected officials, and to common sense that shows &lt;a href=&#34;https://urbanism.guide/austin/transportation/highways&#34;&gt;highways have been a fatal and failed experiment&lt;/a&gt; in moving people safely and efficiently around the US.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-dark&#34; role=&#34;alert&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 class=&#34;alert-heading&#34;&gt;Rail is faster&lt;/h4&gt;

    If a train ran along I-35 it could get you from &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/0tRYLxNeNV0&#34;&gt;San Antonio to Austin in 38 minutes&lt;/a&gt;, or from San Antonio to Dallas in 2 hours and 8 minutes.

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;rethink35-lawsuit&#34;&gt;Rethink35 Lawsuit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rethink35 and 16 other plaintiffs have sued TxDOT. The lawsuit alleges:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TxDOT didn&amp;rsquo;t properly study other options such as:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://rethink35.org/proposal&#34;&gt;The Rethink 35 proposal&lt;/a&gt; which involved rerouting the highway and replacing it with a boulevard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://reconnectaustin.com/#home-vis-sec&#34;&gt;The Reconnect Austin vision&lt;/a&gt; which called for the highway being placed underground with a boulevard on top.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TxDOT failed to study several air pollutants and their impacts on the people who live near I-35. This includes particulate matter 2.5 (PM2.5) which puts people at increased risk for asthma and other health conditions. Based on new EPA standards, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kut.org/energy-environment/2024-02-19/austin-area-has-dangerously-high-levels-of-air-pollution-according-to-new-epa-standards&#34;&gt;Austin is already above the safe limit&lt;/a&gt;. TxDOT was &lt;a href=&#34;https://my35capex.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/APPROVED-FEIS-ROD_Appendix-G-Comment-Response-Matrix-from-Public-Hearing-Notice-of-Availability-of-DEIS_2023-08-14.pdf&#34;&gt;aware of this concern&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There was &lt;a href=&#34;https://my35capex.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/APPROVED-FEIS-ROD_Appendix-A-Project-Location-Map_2023-08-14.pdf&#34;&gt;a significant change to the water outfall&lt;/a&gt; that was made after the Draft Environmental Impact Statement was published and so there was no opportunity for public comment. Polluted runoff from the highway will exit into &lt;a href=&#34;https://naturerocksaustin.org/greenspace/colorado-river-preserve&#34;&gt;a wildlife preserve in East Austin&lt;/a&gt;; around US-183 and the Colorado River.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;civil-rights-title-vi-complaint&#34;&gt;Civil Rights (Title VI) Complaint&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rethink35 has also &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/24390031-rethink35-title-vi-complaint-filed&#34;&gt;filed a Title VI civil rights complaint&lt;/a&gt;. The complaint alleges:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I-35 was built to be intentionally discriminatory by replacing East Ave and solidifying a line of segregation between East and West Austin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under Title VI, agencies with a history of prior discrimination have a responsibility to take affirmative action to redress previous injustices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instead, this project exacerbates these very same harmful practices by:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Displacing people from homes and businesses. 86% of the displaced are in Environmental Justice communities (ie. low income, and people of color).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More than doubling the number of lane miles of I-35. Thus widening the barrier between East and West Austin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dumping polluted storm water into a Wildlife Sanctuary in East Austin, continuing a long-standing pattern of moving environmental waste from downtown to East Austin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Worsening air quality, climate change, and increasing summer temperatures, all of which disproportionately burden communities of color.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-primary&#34; role=&#34;alert&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 class=&#34;alert-heading&#34;&gt;Highways as segregation tools&lt;/h4&gt;

    Highway construction and expansion is one of many tools used to systematically segregate our cities. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://urbanism.guide/austin/housing/housing_segregation&#34;&gt;history of housing segregation&lt;/a&gt; is as brutal as it is banal. These injustices persist to the present day.

&lt;/div&gt;


      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
