<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Urbanism.guide – Housing</title><link>/austin/housing/</link><description>Recent content in Housing on Urbanism.guide</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="/austin/housing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Austin: Affordable Housing</title><link>/austin/housing/affordable_housing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/austin/housing/affordable_housing/</guid><description>
&lt;p>Affordable housing is a term that has many meanings depending on who you&amp;rsquo;re talking to and what you&amp;rsquo;re talking about.
Most generally affordable housing can be broken down into two major categories:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Housing affordability for people within a certain household income level as defined by the City of Austin&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Housing affordability for you, and others in a general sense&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Both of these are entirely legitimate concerns and ways to think about housing, so we&amp;rsquo;ll discuss them both and some of the ways in which affordability has been and can continue to be addressed. However it&amp;rsquo;s important to keep in mind that housing affordability is one large piece of a big puzzle that includes cost of transit, utilities, and services.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="city-of-austin-housing-affordability-initiatives">City of Austin Housing Affordability Initiatives&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Housing security is one of several important safety nets that are crucial to a healthy and functioning society.
Towards this end cities often implement policies to help ensure people remain with housing and without undue hardship.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Within the city of Austin these initiatives have taken the form of:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Affordability Unlocked&lt;/li>
&lt;li>VMU1/2&lt;/li>
&lt;li>TOD/ETOD&lt;/li>
&lt;li>HOME&lt;/li>
&lt;li>SMART&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>There are also federal programs which we won&amp;rsquo;t discuss here as they&amp;rsquo;re outside the scope of this article&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="alert alert-primary" role="alert">
&lt;h4 class="alert-heading">Median Family Income&lt;/h4>
The income levels mentioned below are based on &lt;a href="https://www.austintexas.gov/sites/default/files/files/Housing_%26_Planning/MFI%20Chart%20Effective_2022.pdf">Median Family Income (MFI)&lt;/a>. MFI is a measure of what the average household earns in the Austin-Round Rock area. The 100% MFI in 2022 was $88,250 for a family of 2 meaning half of all families earned less than this, and half earned more. This could be one family member earning $88,250, or 2 each earning $44,125, or any other split.
&lt;/div>
&lt;h3 id="affordability-unlocked-au">Affordability Unlocked (AU)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.austintexas.gov/department/affordability-unlocked-development-bonus-program">Affordability unlocked&lt;/a> is a program created by the City of Austin in 2019 (&lt;a href="https://services.austintexas.gov/edims/document.cfm?id=319975">original text&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://www.austintexas.gov/sites/default/files/files/Housing/AU_Applicant_Guide_FINAL_1019.pdf">AU guide&lt;/a>) to address housing affordability without subsidizing the housing with taxes. The plan achieves this by allowing developers who apply for Affordability Unlocked to build housing that is up to 25-50% taller than the current zoning limitations. This program is most commonly used in tandem with Multi-family zoning and &lt;a href="https://services.austintexas.gov/edims/document.cfm?id=383601">VMU combining zoning districts&lt;/a> along transit corridors where residents would have close and convenient access to public transit.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In practical terms this means that buildings using Affordability unlocked are able to build rentable and ownable housing for those living at or under 80% of the Median Family Income (MFI) of Austin&amp;rsquo;s citizens. Affordability Unlocked is further divided into two types, aptly called Type 1, and Type 2.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Under Type 1 at least half of all units built must be affordable. For rentals they must be kept affordable for a minimum of 40 years for those earning between 20% ($17,650) to 50% MFI ($44,150). For ownable units they must be kept affordable for a minimum of 99 years for those earning incomes averaging up to 80% MFI ($70,600).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Under Type 2 at least three quarters of all units must be affordable and meet all Type 1 requirements. In addition they must locate the building within a quarter-mile of a transit corridor and designate at least 10% of affordable housing for those earning under 30% MFI ($26,500).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As of 2023 over 3,000 units of housing have been built or are under construction with this program with another 3,000 units in the planning stages. Incredibly 80% of all planned and built housing units under this plan meet the affordability requirements of AU, exceeding the minimums set in place by the program.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="vertical-mixed-use-zoning-vmu1--vmu2">Vertical Mixed Use Zoning (VMU1 &amp;amp; VMU2)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://services.austintexas.gov/edims/document.cfm?id=383601">Vertical Mixed Use zoning&lt;/a> is a provision applied along major existing and future transit corridors with the goal of getting more of Austin&amp;rsquo;s citizens close to transit with mixed-use development that provides both housing and retail development. This zoning addresses affordability in multiple ways:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Allowing for more units of housing to be built along these corridors&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Placing homes closer to current and future affordable transit options&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Creating easier access to the daily conveniences people need&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The original VMU zoning (VMU1) was introduced in 2010 and allowed for reducing setbacks, mixed use development (residential and commercial), and reduced parking minimums along with other considerations that allow for denser housing. Along with this VMU1 set out small allowances of 10% affordable housing for rental and ownership developments.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>VMU1 has thus far succeeded in creating over 100 new buildings under this zoning and as such was &lt;a href="https://services.austintexas.gov/edims/document.cfm?id=371876">expanded with VMU2&lt;/a> that allows for buildings zoned for high density multifamily residences (MF-6) to reach 90 feet in height by right (ie. by default). VMU1 buildings are typically limited to 60 feet or less. Both VMU1 and VMU2 can be kept lower due to &lt;a href="/austin/housing/compatibility_restrictions">compatibility restrictions&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="equitable-transit-oriented-development-tod--etod">Equitable Transit Oriented Development (TOD / ETOD)&lt;/h3>
&lt;div class="pageinfo pageinfo-info">
&lt;p>This section/topic is incomplete. If you have some knowledge on this subject please help out by &lt;a href="https://github.com/zeezephyr/urbanism-guide/edit/dev/content/en/austin/housing/affordable_housing.md">editing this page.&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;h3 id="home-options-for-middle-income-empowerment-home">Home Options for Middle-income Empowerment (HOME)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>One of the key hindrances to housing affordability is the availability of housing. Within Austin, and most US cities, supply has been artificially restricted for over half a century. Today Austin has a housing code (aka Land Development Code) that was last updated in the 1980s with the idea that it&amp;rsquo;s important to keep property sizes very large, and housing very limited, so that only those with high means can enjoy living here.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://services.austintexas.gov/edims/document.cfm?id=411485">HOME is an initiative&lt;/a> very much representative of today&amp;rsquo;s generational housing conflict. It&amp;rsquo;s currently (as of Oct 2023) being considered by City Council with overwhelming support while simultaneously being the target of anti-housing activists.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>HOME allows for the building of more housing and better neighborhoods by:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Reducing residential minimum lot sizes from 5,750 sq ft to 2,500 sq ft.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Allowing up to 3 units of housing to be built on a lot without additional zoning changes to the lot&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Quite literally the city council wants to do what urbanists have been asking of it. Enable more neighborhoods to follow the design principles of livable, walkable, nice areas. Transforming what is currently a limited luxury for the well off of our city into something that everyone who lives in Austin can enjoy. This doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean all of our neighborhoods will end up looking like any specific place, just that we&amp;rsquo;ll have more flexibility in what we build and who we build it for.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="/media/homes_like_mueller.png" alt="A screenshot of the HOME resolution that says: &amp;ldquo;The City Manager is encouraged to propose changes that are informed by the design principles developed in the Mueller Plan and other similar resources. At minimum, the City Manager is directed to propose amendments that will&amp;rdquo;">&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="alert alert-primary" role="alert">
&lt;h4 class="alert-heading">Minimum Lot Size&lt;/h4>
Austin&amp;rsquo;s minimum lot size will still remain quite big relative to nearby cities. Houston for example has a minimum lot size of 1,400 sq ft!
&lt;/div>
&lt;h3 id="smart">SMART&lt;/h3>
&lt;div class="pageinfo pageinfo-info">
&lt;p>This section/topic is incomplete. If you have some knowledge on this subject please help out by &lt;a href="https://github.com/zeezephyr/urbanism-guide/edit/dev/content/en/austin/housing/affordable_housing.md">editing this page.&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;h2 id="housing-affordability-in-general">Housing Affordability in General&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Housing affordability in general requires a multi-pronged approach so that housing prices can be brought down to a point where
they are affordable to those living above the income levels defined by CoA. It&amp;rsquo;s not hard to see how even those earning $100,000+ a year
are struggling to afford housing. Housing affordability across the US has dropped steeply and this is driven by many factors including:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Interest rates on loans&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Severe zoning restrictions on housing&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Parking minimums on new construction&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Tax structures which disincentivize building housing&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="/austin/housing/compatibility_restrictions">Compatibility restrictions&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Unrealistic lot size minimums&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Deed restrictions&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;Valid Petition&amp;rdquo; laws&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h3 id="interest-rates-on-loans">Interest rates on loans&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Much like with the student loan crisis the housing affordability crisis is affected by the availability of loans and low interest rates. However this is a very complex topic and outside the scope of a guide to urbanism as it is not something urbanism can solve directly. Within the context of housing urbanism is principally concerned with the supply side of the housing market (ie. the total amount of homes available for people to live in) while interest rates primarily influence the demand side of the housing market (ie. money people have to purchase property). Furthermore the situation our housing market is in, particularly on the limited supply side of housing, has not been seen before in the US and as such what we know historically about interest rates, loans, and housing may no longer apply.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Of course no understanding of the situation we are in is complete without some understanding of the effect interest rates have on housing costs so here&amp;rsquo;s a few resources if you&amp;rsquo;re interested. Just know that this subject is tangential to urbanism rather than central. Urbanism doesn&amp;rsquo;t need to address interest rates to fix the housing crisis.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.investopedia.com/articles/mortgages-real-estate/08/interest-rates-affect-property-values.asp">How Interest Rates Affect Property Values&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.urban.org/urban-wire/how-higher-mortgage-rates-have-historically-affected-home-prices">How Higher Mortgage Rates Have Historically Affected Home Prices&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20230516081511/https://www.nytimes.com/2022/03/31/upshot/home-prices-mortgage-rates.html">Can Home Prices and Interest Rates Soar at the Same Time?&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="zoning-restrictions-on-housing">Zoning restrictions on housing&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Austin, like most US cities, has an overwhelming amount of its residential living space is zoned exclusively for single family free standing homes on large lots. Within Austin the minimum lot size you can currently build a single family home on is 5,750 square feet and within that lot you can only build a house and other impervious ground cover on 40% of it. 60% of your lot must be left as unused space. This is leading to various crises in the housing market ranging from entire generations of young people being priced out of affordable housing to older generations &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20230829054538/https://www.nytimes.com/2022/11/27/us/living-alone-aging.html">living alone in large homes&lt;/a> and unable to find smaller homes to down size to.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="parking-minimums">Parking minimums&lt;/h3>
&lt;div class="pageinfo pageinfo-info">
&lt;p>This section/topic is incomplete. If you have some knowledge on this subject please help out by &lt;a href="https://github.com/zeezephyr/urbanism-guide/edit/dev/content/en/austin/housing/affordable_housing.md">editing this page.&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;h3 id="tax-structures-favoring-empty-lots">Tax structures favoring empty lots&lt;/h3>
&lt;div class="pageinfo pageinfo-info">
&lt;p>This section/topic is incomplete. If you have some knowledge on this subject please help out by &lt;a href="https://github.com/zeezephyr/urbanism-guide/edit/dev/content/en/austin/housing/affordable_housing.md">editing this page.&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;h3 id="unrealistic-lot-size-minimums">Unrealistic lot size minimums&lt;/h3>
&lt;div class="pageinfo pageinfo-info">
&lt;p>This section/topic is incomplete. If you have some knowledge on this subject please help out by &lt;a href="https://github.com/zeezephyr/urbanism-guide/edit/dev/content/en/austin/housing/affordable_housing.md">editing this page.&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Austin: Compatibility Restrictions</title><link>/austin/housing/compatibility_restrictions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/austin/housing/compatibility_restrictions/</guid><description>
&lt;h2 id="in-austin">In Austin&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Austin has some of the most restrictive compatibility requirements within the United States. Austin&amp;rsquo;s current compatibility restrictions are such that:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A building within 50 feet of a SFH&amp;rsquo;s lot cannot be more than 40 feet tall.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A building within 300 feet of a SFH&amp;rsquo;s lot cannot be more than 60 feet tall.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="/media/sfh_compatibility_distance.png" alt="A chart showing the full range of housing compatibility restrictions which extends from 25 feet at the property line limiting housing to 40 feet tall all the way to 540 feet of distance from a SFH restricting building height to 120 feet">
&lt;a href="https://services.austintexas.gov/edims/document.cfm?id=414928">Source: Findings and Recommendations for Implementing Ordinance No. 20221201-056 Regarding Compatibility Regulations, Sept 5 2023&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Effectively this means that tens of thousands of homes are currently illegal to build in Austin even in areas that are zoned for slightly denser housing. If you&amp;rsquo;ve ever noticed buildings within Austin that look like steps, getting progressively taller/shorter, this is compatibility. An artificial, and inequitable restriction on the amount of housing that can be built.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Austin compatibility is also atypically extreme compared to most other cities. As shown in this chart where Austin has decided that the presence of a single family home can affect housing that is being built 2 blocks away.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="/media/austin_compatibility_vs_other_cities.png" alt="A chart showing that Austin compatibility restrictions are 2-3x in excess of the average compatibility for comparable cities">
&lt;a href="https://services.austintexas.gov/edims/document.cfm?id=414928">Source: Findings and Recommendations for Implementing Ordinance No. 20221201-056 Regarding Compatibility Regulations, Sept 5 2023&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="effects-of-compatibility">Effects of Compatibility&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The failure of compatibility does not stop at simply housing. It also has effects on transportation, equity, the environment, and car dependency.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A &lt;a href="https://services.austintexas.gov/edims/document.cfm?id=414927">recent study by the City of Austin on Compatibility Regulations&lt;/a> (September, 2023) found that 135,000 housing units are lost in areas already zoned for high density due to compatibility rules. 110,000 of the lost units (82%) are within 1/4th of a mile of an existing transit stop.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Compatibility triggers even when no homes exist on a lot. It requires that if an area is zoned for single family housing then that is enough to restrict what can be built by it. In this way almost completely empty pieces of land, such as the one pictured below, limit what housing can be built around it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="/media/camp_mabry_triggers_compatibility.png" alt="The headquarters of the Texas National Guard is zoned for single family homes and triggers compatibility, preventing more housing from being built">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The less dense we can build in places intended for density the less efficient we can make public transit. The less practical we make walking and biking the more we force people into their cars and onto highways to live out their basic needs. The more we inhibit progress on making it possible to live in an environmentally friendly way the worse off we will be. The minor and petty sensibilities of someone who doesn&amp;rsquo;t like slightly taller buildings should not even be a consideration and yet it is currently central to controlling how Austinites are allowed to live.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>