<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Urbanism.guide: Development Site – Housing</title>
    <link>https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/housing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Housing on Urbanism.guide: Development Site</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	  <atom:link href="https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/housing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
      
        
      
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Austin: Affordable Housing</title>
      <link>https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/housing/affordable_housing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/housing/affordable_housing/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;Affordable housing is a term that has many meanings depending on who you&amp;rsquo;re talking to and what you&amp;rsquo;re talking about.
Most generally affordable housing can be broken down into two major categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Capital-A Affordability for people living within a certain household income level as defined by the City of Austin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Market-rate affordability (ie. the present day cost of housing)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of these are entirely legitimate concerns and ways to think about housing, so we&amp;rsquo;ll discuss them both and some of the ways in which affordability has been and can continue to be addressed. However it&amp;rsquo;s important to keep in mind that housing affordability is one large piece of a big puzzle that includes cost of transit, utilities, and services.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-primary&#34; role=&#34;alert&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 class=&#34;alert-heading&#34;&gt;Find Affordable Housing&lt;/h4&gt;

    If you&amp;rsquo;re in need of affordable housing the City of Austin &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.atxaffordablehousing.net/&#34;&gt;has a search tool for finding Affordable housing&lt;/a&gt;. There are also &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.austintexas.gov/page/resources-renters&#34;&gt;numerous other resources&lt;/a&gt; for landlord issues, evictions, rent and utility assistance, and more.

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;city-of-austin-housing-affordability-initiatives&#34;&gt;City of Austin Housing Affordability Initiatives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Housing security is one of several important safety nets that are crucial to a healthy and functioning society.
Towards this end cities often implement policies to help ensure people remain with housing and without undue hardship. Austin itself has had about a dozen different initiatives with varying rates of success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the most impactful initiatives in terms of units built have been:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Affordability Unlocked&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vertical Mixed Use Zoning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Planned Unit Development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-primary&#34; role=&#34;alert&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 class=&#34;alert-heading&#34;&gt;Median Family Income&lt;/h4&gt;

    The income levels mentioned below are based on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.austintexas.gov/sites/default/files/files/Housing_%26_Planning/MFI%20Chart%20Effective_2022.pdf&#34;&gt;Median Family Income (MFI)&lt;/a&gt;. MFI is a measure of what the average household earns in the Austin-Round Rock area. The 100% MFI in 2022 was $88,250 for a family of 2 meaning half of all families earned less than this, and half earned more. This could be one family member earning $88,250, or 2 each earning $44,125, or any other split.

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;affordability-unlocked-au&#34;&gt;Affordability Unlocked (AU)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.austintexas.gov/department/affordability-unlocked-development-bonus-program&#34;&gt;Affordability unlocked&lt;/a&gt; is a program created by the City of Austin in 2019 (&lt;a href=&#34;https://services.austintexas.gov/edims/document.cfm?id=319975&#34;&gt;original text&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.austintexas.gov/sites/default/files/files/Housing/AU_Applicant_Guide_FINAL_1019.pdf&#34;&gt;AU guide&lt;/a&gt;) to address housing affordability without subsidizing the housing with taxes. The plan achieves this by allowing developers who apply for Affordability Unlocked to build housing that is up to 25-50% taller than the current zoning limitations. This program is most commonly used in tandem with Multi-family zoning and &lt;a href=&#34;https://services.austintexas.gov/edims/document.cfm?id=383601&#34;&gt;VMU combining zoning districts&lt;/a&gt; along transit corridors where residents would have close and convenient access to public transit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practical terms this means that buildings using Affordability unlocked are able to build rentable and ownable housing for those living at or under 80% of the Median Family Income (MFI) of Austin&amp;rsquo;s citizens. Affordability Unlocked is further divided into two types, aptly called Type 1, and Type 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under Type 1 at least half of all units built must be affordable. For rentals they must be kept affordable for a minimum of 40 years for those earning between 20% ($17,650) to 50% MFI ($44,150). For ownable units they must be kept affordable for a minimum of 99 years for those earning incomes averaging up to 80% MFI ($70,600).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under Type 2 at least three quarters of all units must be affordable and meet all Type 1 requirements. In addition they must locate the building within a quarter-mile of a transit corridor and designate at least 10% of affordable housing for those earning under 30% MFI ($26,500).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of 2023 over 480 units of housing have been built, 2800 are under construction, and a further 2,800 units are in the planning stages. Incredibly 80% of all planned and built housing units under this plan meet the affordability requirements of AU, exceeding the minimums set in place by the program itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;vertical-mixed-use-zoning-vmu1--vmu2&#34;&gt;Vertical Mixed Use Zoning (VMU1 &amp;amp; VMU2)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://services.austintexas.gov/edims/document.cfm?id=383601&#34;&gt;Vertical Mixed Use zoning&lt;/a&gt; is a provision applied along major existing and future transit corridors with the goal of getting more of Austin&amp;rsquo;s citizens close to transit with mixed-use development that provides both housing and retail development. This zoning addresses affordability in multiple ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allowing for more units of housing to be built along these corridors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Placing homes closer to current and future affordable transit options&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creating easier access to the daily conveniences people need&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original VMU zoning (VMU1) was introduced in 2010 and allowed for reducing setbacks, mixed use development (residential and commercial), reduced parking minimums, and increased building heights; typically up to 60 feet. Along with this VMU1 set out small allowances of 10% affordable housing for rental and ownership developments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VMU1 has thus far succeeded in creating over 100 new buildings under this zoning and as such was &lt;a href=&#34;https://services.austintexas.gov/edims/document.cfm?id=371876&#34;&gt;expanded with VMU2&lt;/a&gt; that allows for buildings zoned for high density multifamily residences (MF-6) to reach 90 feet in height by right (ie. by default); along with a 12% affordable housing minimum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both VMU1 and VMU2 can be kept lower in height due to &lt;a href=&#34;https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/housing/compatibility_restrictions&#34;&gt;compatibility restrictions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-primary&#34; role=&#34;alert&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 class=&#34;alert-heading&#34;&gt;VMU overturned&lt;/h4&gt;

    Unfortunately a lawsuit by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.austinmonitor.com/stories/2023/11/city-loses-second-suit-over-development-rules/&#34;&gt;anti-housing advocates overturned VMU2&lt;/a&gt; on notification grounds. However this story is not over and continued pro-housing advocacy will bring about better and stronger initiatives. Maybe &lt;a href=&#34;https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/get_involved&#34;&gt;get involved&lt;/a&gt; and help us make Austin better!

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;planned-unit-development&#34;&gt;Planned Unit Development&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;pageinfo pageinfo-info&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This section/topic is incomplete. If you have some knowledge on this subject please help out by &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zeezephyr/urbanism-guide/edit/dev/content/en/austin/housing/affordable_housing.md&#34;&gt;editing this page.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;housing-affordability-in-general&#34;&gt;Housing Affordability in General&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Housing affordability in general requires a multi-pronged approach so that housing prices can be brought down to a point where
they are affordable to those living above the income levels defined by CoA. It&amp;rsquo;s not hard to see how even those earning at and above Austin&amp;rsquo;s median income
are struggling to afford housing. Housing affordability across the US has dropped steeply and this is driven by many factors including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Land use policies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interest rates on loans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unrealistic lot size minimums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/transportation/parking&#34;&gt;Parking mandates&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tax structures which disincentivize building housing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/housing/compatibility_restrictions&#34;&gt;Compatibility restrictions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deed restrictions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Valid Petition&amp;rdquo; laws&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;land-use-policies&#34;&gt;Land Use Policies&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-primary&#34; role=&#34;alert&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 class=&#34;alert-heading&#34;&gt;HOME Phase 1 Passes!&lt;/h4&gt;

    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.austinchronicle.com/daily/news/2023-12-08/after-long-day-of-testimony-council-votes-to-end-single-family-zoning/&#34;&gt;HOME Phase 1 passed city council by a supermajority 9-2 vote&lt;/a&gt; on December 7th, 2023. HOME Phase 2 will likely be considered early next year. It&amp;rsquo;s never been a better time to &lt;a href=&#34;https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/get_involved&#34;&gt;get involved&lt;/a&gt;!

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key hindrances to housing affordability is the availability of housing. Within Austin, and most US cities, supply has been artificially restricted for at least a century. Today Austin has a housing code (aka Land Development Code; LDC) that was last updated in the 1980s along with very large lot size minimums that were last updated in the 1940s; the history of which we cover in our article on &lt;a href=&#34;https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/housing/zoning_restrictions&#34;&gt;euclidean zoning restrictions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Austin City Council is addressing these overly restrictive and exclusionary zoning restrictions with an &lt;a href=&#34;https://services.austintexas.gov/edims/document.cfm?id=411485&#34;&gt;initiative called HOME&lt;/a&gt;. This initiative is designed to revamp our outdated land development code by allowing more housing to be built within the core of Austin. Housing that used to exist here but was made illegal in 1984.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HOME is planned in two phases that collectively allow for the building of more housing and better neighborhoods by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reducing residential minimum lot sizes from 5,750 sq ft to 2,500 sq ft.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allowing up to 3 units of housing to be built on a lot without additional zoning changes to the lot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making various other adjustments to the LDC that you can read about on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.atxhomecoalition.com/&#34;&gt;atxhomecoalition.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HOME will allow more neighborhoods to follow the design principles of livable, walkable, nice areas. Transforming what is currently a limited luxury for the well off of our city into something that everyone who lives in Austin can enjoy. This doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean all of our neighborhoods will end up looking like any specific place, just that we&amp;rsquo;ll have more flexibility in what we build, who we build it for, and what it costs.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-primary&#34; role=&#34;alert&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 class=&#34;alert-heading&#34;&gt;Minimum Lot Size&lt;/h4&gt;

    Austin&amp;rsquo;s minimum lot size will still remain quite big relative to nearby cities. Houston for example has a minimum lot size of 1,400 sq ft!

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;interest-rates-on-loans&#34;&gt;Interest rates on loans&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much like with the student loan crisis the housing affordability crisis is affected by the availability of loans and low interest rates. However this is a very complex topic and outside the scope of a guide to urbanism as it is not something urbanism can solve directly. Within the context of housing urbanism is principally concerned with the supply side of the housing market (ie. the total amount of homes available for people to live in) while interest rates primarily influence the demand side of the housing market (ie. money people have to purchase property).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course no understanding of the situation we are in is complete without some understanding of the effect interest rates have on housing costs so here&amp;rsquo;s a few resources if you&amp;rsquo;re interested. Just know that this subject is tangential to urbanism rather than central. Urbanism doesn&amp;rsquo;t need to address interest rates to fix the housing crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.investopedia.com/articles/mortgages-real-estate/08/interest-rates-affect-property-values.asp&#34;&gt;How Interest Rates Affect Property Values&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.urban.org/urban-wire/how-higher-mortgage-rates-have-historically-affected-home-prices&#34;&gt;How Higher Mortgage Rates Have Historically Affected Home Prices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20230516081511/https://www.nytimes.com/2022/03/31/upshot/home-prices-mortgage-rates.html&#34;&gt;Can Home Prices and Interest Rates Soar at the Same Time?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;unrealistic-lot-size-minimums&#34;&gt;Unrealistic lot size minimums&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Austin, like most US cities, has an overwhelming amount of its residential living space zoned exclusively for single family free standing homes on large lots. Within Austin the minimum lot size you can currently build a single family home on is 5,750 square feet and within that lot you can only build a house and other impervious ground cover on 40% of it. 60% of your lot must be left as unused space. This is leading to various crises in the housing market ranging from entire generations of young people being priced out of affordable housing to older generations &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20230829054538/https://www.nytimes.com/2022/11/27/us/living-alone-aging.html&#34;&gt;living alone in large homes&lt;/a&gt; and unable to find smaller homes to downsize to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;tax-structures-favoring-empty-lots&#34;&gt;Tax structures favoring empty lots&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;pageinfo pageinfo-info&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This section/topic is incomplete. If you have some knowledge on this subject please help out by &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zeezephyr/urbanism-guide/edit/dev/content/en/austin/housing/affordable_housing.md&#34;&gt;editing this page.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Austin: Compatibility Restrictions</title>
      <link>https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/housing/compatibility_restrictions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/housing/compatibility_restrictions/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;h2 id=&#34;in-austin&#34;&gt;In Austin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Austin has some of the most restrictive compatibility requirements within the United States. Austin&amp;rsquo;s current compatibility restrictions are such that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A building within 50 feet of a SFH&amp;rsquo;s lot cannot be more than 40 feet tall.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A building within 300 feet of a SFH&amp;rsquo;s lot cannot be more than 60 feet tall.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/media/sfh_compatibility_distance.png&#34; alt=&#34;A chart showing the full range of housing compatibility restrictions which extends from 25 feet at the property line limiting housing to 40 feet tall all the way to 540 feet of distance from a SFH restricting building height to 120 feet&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://services.austintexas.gov/edims/document.cfm?id=414928&#34;&gt;Source: Findings and Recommendations for Implementing Ordinance No. 20221201-056 Regarding Compatibility Regulations, Sept 5 2023&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effectively this means that tens of thousands of homes are currently illegal to build in Austin even in areas that are zoned for slightly denser housing. If you&amp;rsquo;ve ever noticed buildings within Austin that look like steps, getting progressively taller/shorter, this is compatibility. An artificial, and inequitable restriction on the amount of housing that can be built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Austin compatibility is also atypically extreme compared to most other cities. As shown in this chart where Austin has decided that the presence of a single family home can affect housing that is being built 2 blocks away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/media/austin_compatibility_vs_other_cities.png&#34; alt=&#34;A chart showing that Austin compatibility restrictions are 2-3x in excess of the average compatibility for comparable cities&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://services.austintexas.gov/edims/document.cfm?id=414928&#34;&gt;Source: Findings and Recommendations for Implementing Ordinance No. 20221201-056 Regarding Compatibility Regulations, Sept 5 2023&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;effects-of-compatibility&#34;&gt;Effects of Compatibility&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The failure of compatibility does not stop at simply housing. It also has effects on transportation, equity, the environment, and car dependency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://services.austintexas.gov/edims/document.cfm?id=414927&#34;&gt;recent study by the City of Austin on Compatibility Regulations&lt;/a&gt; (September, 2023) found that 135,000 housing units are lost in areas already zoned for high density due to compatibility rules. 110,000 of the lost units (82%) are within 1/4th of a mile of an existing transit stop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compatibility triggers even when no homes exist on a lot. It requires that if an area is zoned for single family housing then that is enough to restrict what can be built by it. In this way almost completely empty pieces of land, such as the one pictured below, limit what housing can be built around it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/media/camp_mabry_triggers_compatibility.png&#34; alt=&#34;The headquarters of the Texas National Guard is zoned for single family homes and triggers compatibility, preventing more housing from being built&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The less dense we can build in places intended for density the less efficient we can make public transit. The less practical we make walking and biking the more we force people into their cars and onto highways to live out their basic needs. The more we inhibit progress on making it possible to live in an environmentally friendly way the worse off we will be. The minor and petty sensibilities of someone who doesn&amp;rsquo;t like slightly taller buildings should not even be a consideration and yet it is currently central to controlling how Austinites are allowed to live.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Austin: Housing Segregation</title>
      <link>https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/housing/housing_segregation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/housing/housing_segregation/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-primary&#34; role=&#34;alert&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 class=&#34;alert-heading&#34;&gt;Learn More About Housing Segregation&lt;/h4&gt;

    &amp;ldquo;The Color of Law&amp;rdquo; by Richard Rothstein served as the initial impetus and a great deal of inspiration for this article. If you want the full story of the egregious extent that all levels of US government and society went towards creating segregation then get yourself a copy. You can even check it out &lt;a href=&#34;https://austin.bibliocommons.com/v2/record/S67C1782566&#34;&gt;at the Austin Public Library&lt;/a&gt;.

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--TODO: Maybe add https://ulidigitalmarketing.blob.core.windows.net/ulidcnc/sites/6/2021/11/ShapingAustin_ULInsights_Nov16.2021.pdf  to above call out --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Housing segregation is neither natural nor unique to Austin. Rather it is something that has been intentionally created and enforced through local, state, and federal laws and agencies. It took every conceivable form and its remnants continue to exist today. Our country&amp;rsquo;s wounds are deep, &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/1044389420923469&#34;&gt;have not ended&lt;/a&gt;, and they still have long to heal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The forms it took are as numerous and creative as you can imagine. From local &lt;a href=&#34;https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/housing/zoning_restrictions&#34;&gt;racial and euclidean zoning&lt;/a&gt;, neighborhood associations, and racial deed restrictions (aka. covenants). To state and country-wide highway expansion. To federal housing loans, public housing, and redlining. To the free market exploiting segregation in the form of blockbusting, contract sales, and 2008&amp;rsquo;s subprime mortgage crisis. Racist and exclusionary housing practices are not over either; recently &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cnn.com/2023/12/14/business/navy-federal-credit-union-black-applicants-invs/index.html&#34;&gt;Navy FCU was accused of systematically denying loan applications&lt;/a&gt; to qualified Black Americans who served in our armed forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intentional and legalized housing segregation continues to plague our cities and towns today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While many banks also approved White applicants at higher rates than Black borrowers, the nearly 29-percentage-point gap in Navy Federal’s approval rates was the widest of any of the 50 lenders that originated the most mortgage loans last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disparity remains even among White and Black applicants who had similar incomes and debt-to-income ratios. Notably, Navy Federal approved a slightly higher percentage of applications from White borrowers making less than $62,000 a year than it did of Black borrowers making $140,000 or more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cnn.com/2023/12/14/business/navy-federal-credit-union-black-applicants-invs/index.html&#34;&gt;Casey Tolan, Audrey Ash, &amp;amp; Rene Marsh via CNN&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-the-impacts-on-people&#34;&gt;A Note on The Impacts on People&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below we describe the significant ways that our government and society created segregation both in Austin and throughout the US. But equally important is to keep in mind how the people who were victims of these policies were forced to live. They were living in poorly constructed housing that was intentionally placed far from work and &amp;ldquo;white&amp;rdquo; society. Despite this they&amp;rsquo;d often be paying much more for housing than other Americans due to limited options, and higher interest rates from private loans. As a result they&amp;rsquo;d often be forced to work multiple jobs, take on extra roommates, and have little time or energy to maintain their already poorly constructed housing. They&amp;rsquo;d have their roads less paved, their sewers less serviced, and other utilities and services neglected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many racist stereotypes that exist today come from these conditions. Conditions that are forced on Black Americans and immigrant populations throughout our history. But as is often the case in America, Black Americans seem to get the worst of it; and we must do much better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;deed-restrictions--racial-covenants&#34;&gt;Deed Restrictions / Racial Covenants&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you live in a single family home on the west side of Austin it is very likely that your property has a deed restriction. It&amp;rsquo;s likely old, filed with the city, and was provided by your title company when you closed on your home. It may detail various things you can and cannot do with your propety from upkeep, to the colors you can paint your home, and the skin color or ethnicity of who is allowed to live in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/media/racist_deed_restrictions.png&#34; alt=&#34;An excerpt of a deed restriction that reads &amp;ldquo;No part of the premises of property covered hereby ever shall be rented, leased, sold, demised or conveyed to, or otherwise become the property of, or into the possession of, any persons other than white persons of strict Caucasian blood.&amp;rdquo;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such restrictions as the one featured above were legal until &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.law.cornell.edu/wex/shelley_v_kraemer_(1948)&#34;&gt;1948 when the Supreme Court case Shelley v. Kramer ruled them illegal&lt;/a&gt;. Except that the Federal Housing Authority which issued home loans kept issuing them to land owners who had racial covenants in their deed restrictions. This practice continued for over a year until Philip Perlman, the US Solicitor General, instituted a policy that prevented the FHA from giving out loans to such properties starting on February 15, 1950. This announcement was given with a grace period presumably so that racists could rush in any remaining racial covenants before the deadline and be grandfathered in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except it didn&amp;rsquo;t end here either. These covenants were then quickly replaced with prohibitively expensive &amp;ldquo;damages&amp;rdquo; that would be charged to land owners who violated a deed restriction and sold land or housing to non-whites. The Supreme Court banned this circumvention in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/346/249/&#34;&gt;1953 case Barrows v. Jackson&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the ultimate unenforceability of any racial covenants in deed restrictions post-1953 they were still able to be included in deed restrictions until a federal appeals court &lt;a href=&#34;https://casetext.com/case/mayers-v-ridley-2/case-summaries&#34;&gt;ruled in 1972 that they violated the Fair Housing Act&lt;/a&gt;. If they couldn&amp;rsquo;t be enforced such racist covenants could at least clearly communicate to would-be home buyers who was welcome and who was not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-primary&#34; role=&#34;alert&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 class=&#34;alert-heading&#34;&gt;Mapping segregation&lt;/h4&gt;

    Many excellent people are &lt;a href=&#34;https://mappingprejudice.umn.edu/covenants-research-nationwide&#34;&gt;working across the US to map racial covenants&lt;/a&gt; in their cities. No such attempt yet exists in Austin.

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;neighborhood-associations&#34;&gt;Neighborhood Associations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neighborhood Associations came into fashion around the 1920s and went hand in hand with racial covenants in deed restrictions by allowing neighbors to enforce racial covenants. Prior to this a deed restriction was between the seller of a house, and the purchaser of a house. If these two parties decided to not be racist then a house could simply be sold or rented to whoever was wanting to buy or live in it as only these parties could enforce the racial covenant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This practice was wide-spread and the difficulty of finding and reading through old deed restrictions has unfortunately left the data on it incomplete. Yet data and examples are still abundant. According to &amp;ldquo;The Color of Law&amp;rdquo; by Richard Rothstein (p. 80) a survey of 300 developments built between 1935-1947 in Queens, Nassau, and Westchester Counties found that 56% of all of them had racial covenants; as did 85% of large developments (75 or more units).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[..] many subdivision developers created a community association before putting homes up for initial sale, and they made membership in it a condition of purchase. Association bylaws usually included a whites-only clause&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.litcharts.com/lit/the-color-of-law&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Color of Law&amp;rdquo; by Richard Rothstein, p. 79&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;public-housing&#34;&gt;Public Housing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1933 the US Government started responding to The Great Depression&amp;rsquo;s significant lack of affordable housing by constructing public housing as part of a series of progressive reforms known as The New Deal. Initially this was done at the federal level under the Public Works Administration (PWA) but shortly thereafter construction would be done at the state level with these projects being approved and funded by the federal United States Housing Authority (USHA).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These housing programs was simultaneously a progressive feat of socialized care for white Americans while also being a driver of segregation, inequity, and upheaval for non-white Americans. It accomplished this through policies of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Building racially segregated housing projects &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Techwood_Homes&#34;&gt;from the very beginning&lt;/a&gt; and in Austin of course; such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://livingnewdeal.org/sites/santa-rita-courts-austin-tx/&#34;&gt;the Santa Rita Courts&lt;/a&gt; for Mexican Americans, Rosewood Courts for Black Americans, and Chalmers Court for white Americans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wholesale demolition of integrated neighborhoods under the auspices of &lt;a href=&#34;https://ulidigitalmarketing.blob.core.windows.net/ulidcnc/sites/6/2021/11/ShapingAustin_ULInsights_Nov16.2021.pdf&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;slum clearance&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enforcing &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nahro.org/journal_article/race-equity-and-housing-the-early-years/&#34;&gt;neighborhood &amp;ldquo;composition&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; rules which turned integrated neighborhoods into segregated neighborhoods.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allowing for poor build quality in non-white neighborhoods (&amp;ldquo;The Color of Law&amp;rdquo;, p. 33).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- TODO
- Systematically placing white neighborhoods close to work and placing non-white neighborhoods next to industrial areas on the outskirts of cities
--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact the first USHA housing projects were constructed in Austin, TX. These projects involved creating separate white, Mexican, and Black housing projects. The white project would be placed closest to downtown, while the Mexican and Black neighborhoods would be placed on the then-outskirts of the city near heavy industry. Further cementing Austin&amp;rsquo;s 1928 master plan to segregate the previously integrated city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;section class=&#34;splide&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;splide__track&#34;&gt;
        &lt;ul class=&#34;splide__list&#34;&gt;
            

&lt;li class=&#34;splide__slide&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img data-splide-lazy=&#39;/media/housing-tracts-usha-1938.png&#39;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
        Throughout the US very little consideration was given to where non-white housing projects would be constructed so long as they were far away from white projects and neighborhoods. 
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&#34;splide__slide&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img data-splide-lazy=&#39;/media/whites-only-usha-housing-1938.png&#39;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
        The first whites-only housing project starts construction in Austin. 
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&#34;splide__slide&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img data-splide-lazy=&#39;/media/slum-clearance-usha-1939.png&#39;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
        Neighborhoods were torn down under the auspices of &amp;#39;slum clearance&amp;#39;. A thinly veiled code word for segregation. 
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;


        &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;


&lt;script src=&#34;https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/main.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
Source: The Austin Statesman; various dates: Feb 1 1938, Dec 23 1938, Jan 31 1939.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;redlining&#34;&gt;Redlining&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;pageinfo pageinfo-info&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This section/topic is incomplete. If you have some knowledge on this subject please help out by &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zeezephyr/urbanism-guide/edit/dev/content/en/austin/housing/housing_segregation.md&#34;&gt;editing this page.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;highway-construction&#34;&gt;Highway Construction&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;pageinfo pageinfo-info&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This section/topic is incomplete. If you have some knowledge on this subject please help out by &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zeezephyr/urbanism-guide/edit/dev/content/en/austin/housing/housing_segregation.md&#34;&gt;editing this page.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--TODO: Add school choice/segregation as a tool to force neighborhood segregation--&gt;
      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Austin: Zoning Restrictions</title>
      <link>https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/housing/zoning_restrictions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://staging.urbanism-guide.pages.dev/austin/housing/zoning_restrictions/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;Zoning is one of the strongest invisible forces that shapes our cities and neighborhoods. Here we&amp;rsquo;ll first cover the history and origins of zoning, then we&amp;rsquo;ll discuss current zoning laws, and finally what is and can be done to fix zoning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-brief-history-of-zoning&#34;&gt;A &amp;ldquo;Brief&amp;rdquo; History of Zoning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put it bluntly, zoning is a direct extension of government mandated and enforced racial segregation. While massive strides have been made with ending Jim Crow laws and forced racial segregation of schools, transportation, and public facilities there still exists the lesser known issue of government enforced segregation of our cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first zoning laws in the US were based on race and this racial zoning was legal within the US until 1917 when it was declared unconstitutional by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buchanan_v._Warley&#34;&gt;Supreme Court in Buchanan v. Warley&lt;/a&gt;. This case was initially prompted by William Warley, a NAACP lawyer, who attempted to buy land in Louisville, Kentucky and occupy a home on it. Louisville had a zoning law that explicitly forbid Black Americans from occupying homes in Louisville. Due to this law William Warley argued he should not have to fulfill his agreement to buy the land because he could not live on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blacks should be quarantined in isolated slums in order to reduce the incidence of civil disturbance, to prevent the spread of communicable disease into nearby white neighborhoods, and to &lt;strong&gt;protect property values&lt;/strong&gt; among the White majority&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; J. Barry Mahool (via &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thebaltimorestory.org/history-1/blog-post-title-four-hc9z5&#34;&gt;thebaltimorestory.org&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately the Supreme Court ruled unanimously that excluding Black Americans from White neighborhoods infringed upon White land-owner&amp;rsquo;s right to sell their property to whomever they wished. Thus any race based zoning was now illegal and unenforceable throughout the US. The court paid no concern to Black American&amp;rsquo;s right to live where they wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;euclidean-zoning&#34;&gt;Euclidean Zoning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the months prior to the 1917 Supreme Court decision the racist and wealthy within US cities got to work devising ways to side step this ruling.  To keep up the violation of American citizen&amp;rsquo;s civil and constitutional rights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A New York City based organization called the Fifth Avenue Association created a campaign that would take racial zoning and make it much more insidious. Rather than excluding based on race or ethnicity the new laws could exclude based on attributes more common to Black, Brown, and White immigrant Americans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first such campaign for this new kind of zoning was termed &amp;ldquo;Save New York&amp;rdquo; and it targeted garment factories on 5th Avenue. However the factories themselves were not really an issue to the Fifth Avenue Association and White New Yorkers. Instead the issue was that garment workers were primarily Jewish and Italian immigrants. If they could legislate away the garment industry they could legislate away these ethnic groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The campaign&amp;rsquo;s goals unfortunately succeeded all too well and the first modern &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zoning_in_the_United_States#Euclidean&#34;&gt;Euclidean zoning&lt;/a&gt; law was enacted in New York on July 25, 1916.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the opening of the 20th century, tens of thousands of garment workers began to clog the streets of Fifth Avenue, strolling and window-shopping, and meeting informally to discuss the vagaries of the trade. For property and business owners along Fifth Avenue, however, the workers constituted nothing short of an immigrant horde that had to be stopped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://garmentdistrict.nyc/sites/default/files/admin-files/2022-04/GD_HistoryBook-ONLINE-lo.pdf&#34;&gt;Source: &amp;ldquo;A Stitch in Time: A History of New York&amp;rsquo;s Garment District&amp;rdquo; by Gabriel Montero&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This new style of zoning quickly spread throughout the US. In fact the first Supreme Court case concerning Euclidean zoning, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Village_of_Euclid_v._Ambler_Realty_Co.&#34;&gt;Euclid v. Amber&lt;/a&gt;, was heard in 1926. The case concerned the Village of Euclid&amp;rsquo;s new zoning law designed to keep &amp;ldquo;industrial Cleveland&amp;rdquo; from changing the &amp;ldquo;character of the village&amp;rdquo;. While a lower court determined that Euclid&amp;rsquo;s zoning law was unconstitutional the Supreme Court ultimately sided with the village and upheld the exclusionary zoning. Now with a Supreme Court decision similar use-based zoning towards discriminatory ends was further emboldened.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-primary&#34; role=&#34;alert&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 class=&#34;alert-heading&#34;&gt;The character of the neighborhood&lt;/h4&gt;

    Be wary of calls to &amp;ldquo;Save&amp;rdquo; neighborhoods and cities. To preserve property values. To protect &amp;ldquo;neighborhood character&amp;rdquo;.

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-city-plan-for-austin&#34;&gt;A City Plan for Austin&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just a few years later Austin penned its first planning document in 1928, &lt;a href=&#34;https://repositories.lib.utexas.edu/handle/2152/65853?show=full&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;A City Plan for Austin, Texas&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; that included bountiful amenities for its White residents, and segregation for its Black residents who would be pushed to the East side and then forgotten about. According to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.litcharts.com/lit/the-color-of-law&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Color of Law&amp;rdquo; by Richard Rothstein&lt;/a&gt; their roads were left less paved, their sewers unmaintained and clogged, and their bus routes suspended in the summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over time more approaches to zoning were devised such as surreptitious &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.austinpolitics.net/a-big-win-for-small-lots/&#34;&gt;increases to minimum lot sizes&lt;/a&gt; from none up until 1929 to 3,000 square feet in 1930, then 3,500 in 1941, and a whopping 5,750 square feet in 1946. Lot sizes were then paired with the creation of single family zoning, setbacks, and so on. Each of these policies serving to further exclude Black and Brown Americans from home ownership by making it prohibitively expensive for them to own property within White neighborhoods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Streets would be widened and paved to account for increasing automobile use (Austinites were already complaining about traffic in 1928). Boulevards would be sculpted and lined with trees. Playgrounds and parks would be built within a half-mile walk of every person in the city [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And black Austinites would be shunted into a new “[black] district.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://puzycki.substack.com/p/the-problem-we-still-live-with&#34;&gt;Source: &amp;ldquo;The Problem We Still Live With&amp;rdquo; by Ryan Puzycki&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And thus we find ourselves with the result: two Austins. One of which has benefited immensely from repeatedly pushing people out and the other which has repeatedly suffered from being pushed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When anti-housing advocates ask to preserve single family zoning, to put all new housing on the East side, and to build further and further away they ask to continue the same segregationist policies that the city has practiced for nearly 100 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;austins-present-day-zoning&#34;&gt;Austin&amp;rsquo;s Present Day Zoning&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;pageinfo pageinfo-info&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This section/topic is incomplete. If you have some knowledge on this subject please help out by &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zeezephyr/urbanism-guide/edit/dev/content/en/austin/housing/zoning_restrictions.md&#34;&gt;editing this page.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fixing-zoning&#34;&gt;Fixing Zoning&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;pageinfo pageinfo-info&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This section/topic is incomplete. If you have some knowledge on this subject please help out by &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zeezephyr/urbanism-guide/edit/dev/content/en/austin/housing/zoning_restrictions.md&#34;&gt;editing this page.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
