<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Your guide to urbanism – Transportation</title>
    <link>https://urbanism.guide/austin/transportation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Transportation on Your guide to urbanism</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	  <atom:link href="https://urbanism.guide/austin/transportation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
      
        
      
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Austin: Biking</title>
      <link>https://urbanism.guide/austin/transportation/biking/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://urbanism.guide/austin/transportation/biking/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;Biking in Austin is becoming more and more accessible with over 230 miles of bike lanes already built. With every bike lane added, with every person out riding bikes, drivers and people in general become more familiar with, aware of, and supportive of biking as a form of commute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biking is not just healthy but also offers many other benefits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s much cheaper than driving. Even an e-bike uses just 5-10 cents of electricity per charge and a typical e-bike has a range of 30-60 miles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s significantly less strain on infrastructure. Bikes cause almost zero damage to roads. Larger, heavier vehicles &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourth_power_law&#34;&gt;are responsible for road damage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Biking is generally a much more pleasant experience than driving. You feel a lot more present, more attached to the world around you, people wave and smile, and you simply move around at more human and lower stressed speeds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;getting-around&#34;&gt;Getting Around&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biking in Austin is becoming more and more accessible with over 230 miles already built. With every bike lane we add we get more and more people out enjoying a simply more pleasant way of commuting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s also important to note that not every commute is fit for biking and keeping your safety and comfort in mind is always the most important thing. Manual biking is most suitable to trips of 3 miles or less which &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.energy.gov/eere/vehicles/articles/fotw-1230-march-21-2022-more-half-all-daily-trips-were-less-three-miles-2021&#34;&gt;make up over half of all trips&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-primary&#34; role=&#34;alert&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 class=&#34;alert-heading&#34;&gt;More distance&lt;/h4&gt;

    With e-bikes your possible biking range is extended considerably and 80% of trips are 10 miles or less!

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you want to start biking check out the links below to find a bike, or start planning routes and finding things that are reasonable and comfortable for you to reach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;aaa-bike-network&#34;&gt;AAA Bike Network&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The city of Austin has planned out an All Ages and Abilities network with the goal of creating over 800 miles of bike lanes across Austin. You can find plans, analysis, and maps of the city&amp;rsquo;s biking network within their &lt;a href=&#34;https://austin.maps.arcgis.com/apps/MapJournal/index.html?appid=dba125033d42453491b36ea5fb935eea&#34;&gt;AAA biking network tool here&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s a great place to get started with seeing what bike lanes are near you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scroll through to find regularly updated maps of what&amp;rsquo;s been finished, what&amp;rsquo;s currently being built, and what&amp;rsquo;s coming! This tool also contains a list of each project, its status, and it&amp;rsquo;s style (known as a treatment type). Style varies from painted bike lanes to fully protected and separated lanes. You can view this info in table format or by clicking on a particular segment on the buildout map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;austin-2023-bicycle-plan&#34;&gt;Austin 2023 Bicycle Plan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Austin recently updated its AAA network plan to make cycling an integral part of the city&amp;rsquo;s transportation network. The biggest improvements over the 2014 plan are a number of new street identified for the AAA network and  a commitment to concrete barrier or planter protection for all protected bike lanes when the network reaches full build-out. You can read the full &lt;a href=&#34;https://acrobat.adobe.com/link/track?uri=urn%3Aaaid%3Ascds%3AUS%3Aab8e2bdd-f183-3e4d-bbc1-187138049fba&#34;&gt;updated AAA 2023 Bicycle Plan here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;austin-energy-e-ride-rebate&#34;&gt;Austin Energy e-Ride Rebate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Austin Energy is currently offering a significant rebate on electric e-Bikes, scooters, mopeds, and motorcycles purchased in Austin. The rebate ranges from $200-$600 depending on the price of the vehicle and there is an even larger rebate of $300-$1,300 for those customers on Austin Energy&amp;rsquo;s Customer Assistance Program (CAP). You can &lt;a href=&#34;https://austinenergy.com/green-power/plug-in-austin/more-ways-to-go-electric/e-ride-rebate&#34;&gt;learn more about the program&lt;/a&gt; on Austin Energy&amp;rsquo;s website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;biking-route-applications&#34;&gt;Biking Route Applications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest and most popular mapping apps unfortunately don&amp;rsquo;t always do the best job giving you the best biking routes. They&amp;rsquo;re still very car-focused and as such tend to not consider the various side streets, short cuts, and slightly longer but safer routes that most bike riders prefer. Fortunately there are many apps available to help you plan your routes such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://citymapper.com/&#34;&gt;Citymapper&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.citymapper.app.release&amp;amp;hl&#34;&gt;Android&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://apps.apple.com/us/app/citymapper-all-live-transit/id469463298&#34;&gt;iOS&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cyclers.app/&#34;&gt;Cyclers&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.umotional.bikeapp&amp;amp;hl=en&#34;&gt;Android&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://apps.apple.com/cz/app/cyclers-bike-map-navigation/id1213867271&#34;&gt;iOS&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.komoot.com/&#34;&gt;Komoot&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?hl=en&amp;amp;id=de.komoot.android&#34;&gt;Android&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://apps.apple.com/us/app/komoot-hike-bike-run/id447374873&#34;&gt;iOS&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Austin: Highways</title>
      <link>https://urbanism.guide/austin/transportation/highways/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://urbanism.guide/austin/transportation/highways/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;TxDOT, CAMPO, and the TTC are the three organizations and political bodies that are responsible for our mess of deadly highways. TTC is a state-wide body of 5 political appointees that plans and authorizes 10 year transportation plans (aka UTPs) at a state level. These plans then get passed to TxDOT who must work with CAMPO to identify projects, funding, and finally approve plans that achieve the goals of the UTP. CAMPO approves federal funding for TxDOT highway projects. Collectively they represent a destructive, unrepresentative, and undemocratic force of will of the oil and gas industry to carve up our cities and environment for profit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;preface-the-cost-of-highways-and-roads&#34;&gt;Preface: The Cost of Highways and Roads&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The true cost of highways and roads is almost never discussed when it comes to budgeting within the US. The necessity of an ever larger amount of road and all their economic, social, and environmental costs are simply taken as-is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the economic side of the equation roads cost the average household $14,000 per year regardless of if they own a car or not. When factoring in car ownership the cost nearly doubles to &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2020/01/massachusetts-car-economy-costs-64-billion-study-finds/&#34;&gt;$26,000 per household per year on average for the total cost of using roads&lt;/a&gt;. We need to ask the question of whether or not we should be paying such astronomical costs for the car economy when more affordable, cleaner, and safer alternatives exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the environmental side, beyond burning fossil fuels, car tires are the second largest source of primary microplastics in our environment producing &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0048969720313358?via%3Dihub#s0050&#34;&gt;3,962,765,390 pounds (1,797,480 tonnes) of microplastic pollution&lt;/a&gt; per year. The US is also the single largest per capita creator of tire-based microplastics due to how much we drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;texas-department-of-transportation-txdot&#34;&gt;Texas Department of Transportation (TxDOT)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Texas Department of Transportation is the state&amp;rsquo;s department that plans and implements roads for cars and trucks on ROWs that they own or have access to use. In principal a Department Of Transportation &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; create transportation options for all modes of transportation. However in practice and in law they spend almost all of their funding on road expansions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TxDOT road expansions include highways as well as many regular streets within cities and towns that they also own. This means that in some cases urbanist efforts to improve certain roads are frustrated by the state&amp;rsquo;s desire to harm its people over petty grievances. Due to this fatal crashes on state owned roadways continue to rise, while on non-state roads fatalities have remained flat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://urbanism.guide/media/txdot_fatalities_increasing.png&#34; alt=&#34;Chart showing a significant increase in fatalities on State owned roads over time&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.austintexas.gov/sites/default/files/files/ATD%20PIO/Vision%20Zero/Vision%20Zero%20Update%2005.25.23.pdf&#34;&gt;Source: Austin Vision Zero Update, May 25 2023&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;txdot-funding&#34;&gt;TxDOT Funding&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://statutes.capitol.texas.gov/Docs/CN/htm/CN.3/CN.3.49-g.v2.htm&#34;&gt;Proposition 1&lt;/a&gt;: Directs 37.5% of existing oil and natural gas production taxes (aka severance) to TxDOT so that &amp;ldquo;the funds may only be used for constructing, maintaining, and acquiring rights-of-way for public roadways other than toll roads.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://statutes.capitol.texas.gov/Docs/CN/htm/CN.8/CN.8.7-c.htm&#34;&gt;Proposition 7&lt;/a&gt;: Directs portions of state sales and use taxes, as well as motor vehicle sale and rental taxes to: &amp;ldquo;(1) construct, maintain, or acquire rights of way for public roadways other than toll roads; or (2) repay the principal of and interest on general obligation bonds issued as authorized by Section 49-p, Article III, of this constitution.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In combination these two propositions have lead to tens of billions of state tax dollars being directed towards maintaining and expanding highways and all the negatives that car dependent infrastructure brings to us and our cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fhwa.dot.gov/bipartisan-infrastructure-law/cmaq.cfm&#34;&gt;Congestion Mitigation and Air Quality (CMAQ) Improvement Program&lt;/a&gt;: This is a federal program which says when a state fails to meet their obligations under the Clean Air Act they can be awarded funding to improve their compliance. However this bill also allows up to 50% of funding to be redirected to other highway and transportation activities. The end result being that states are able to use funding intended for improving our air quality to instead construct additional highways and roads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A State may transfer up to 50% of CMAQ funds made available each fiscal year to any other apportionment of the State, including the National Highway Performance Program, Surface Transportation Block Grant Program, Highway Safety Improvement Program, National Highway Freight Program [..]&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;capital-area-metropolitan-planning-authority-campo&#34;&gt;Capital Area Metropolitan Planning Authority (CAMPO)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Per the CAMPO website:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Capital Area Metropolitan Planning Organization is the metropolitan planning organization for Bastrop, Burnet, Caldwell, Hays, Travis, and Williamson Counties. MPOs are federally required throughout the country in areas with a population of 50,000 or more and are required to produce a 20+ year transportation plan, called a Regional Transportation Plan (RTP), and a four-year planning document called the Transportation Improvement Program (TIP).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CAMPO is governed by a 21-member Transportation Policy Board, made up of 19 elected officials and a representative from TxDOT and one from Capital Metro. The Policy Board is the body that makes decisions on CAMPO policy and decides how CAMPO funding is allocated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;campo-representation&#34;&gt;CAMPO Representation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Austin&amp;rsquo;s 2022 population of 974,447 (2022; US Census Estimate) makes up 39% of the total population represented within CAMPO yet this 21 member board contains only 4 members from Austin which means that Austin&amp;rsquo;s overall voting and decision making power is significantly lower than its population size. This leads to poor decision making that negatively impacts Austin because our needs are not adequately represented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further reducing Ausin&amp;rsquo;s influence and proper representation within CAMPO is the Transportation Policy Board Executive Committee. This 9 member board is the body that makes recommendations to the full TPB board about plans, projects, and issues. Not a single member of this committee is from Austin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There doesn&amp;rsquo;t yet exist a movement in Austin to fix CAMPO so that it is fairly representative or so that Austin can have its own MPO. However similar efforts have been taken up in neighboring cities like where the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fairforhouston.com/&#34;&gt;Fair For Houston initiative&lt;/a&gt; passed with 65% voter approval in November 2023. A similar initiative could be done in Austin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to CAMPO&amp;rsquo;s lack of proper representation for Austin it also actively excludes members of the public by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Locating their meetings at the Junior League on Texas 360 Loop which excludes anyone who commutes without a car from attending. Accessibility to this meeting will get even worse over the next 5 years due to two major highway projects on Loop 360 and Spicewood Springs Road.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Holding all meetings at 2pm on weekdays without an option to dial-in. Effectively excluding anyone who works a daytime job for a living.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Requiring all speakers to attend in person; no option to dial in to comment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;texas-transportation-commission-ttc&#34;&gt;Texas Transportation Commission (TTC)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final piece to the puzzle of how transportation gets built in is the TTC. They are a small body of 5 political appointees that make 10 year plans for CAMPO and TxDOT to fund and implement.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;pageinfo pageinfo-info&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This section/topic is incomplete. If you have some knowledge on this subject please help out by &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zeezephyr/urbanism-guide/edit/dev/content/en/austin/transportation/highways.md&#34;&gt;editing this page.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Austin: Parking Mandates</title>
      <link>https://urbanism.guide/austin/transportation/parking/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://urbanism.guide/austin/transportation/parking/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;h2 id=&#34;a-brief-history-of-parking-mandates&#34;&gt;A Brief History of Parking Mandates&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parking mandates (aka parking minimums) were first created in the 1950s as a measure to provide parking for America&amp;rsquo;s then fledgling car culture. However, according to the Bureau of Transportation Statistics (BTS), these mandates are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bts.gov/archive/publications/journal_of_transportation_and_statistics/volume_06_number_01/paper_01/index&#34;&gt;based on limited and highly inaccurate data&lt;/a&gt; published in a report called &amp;ldquo;Parking Generation&amp;rdquo; by the Institute of Transportation Engineers (ITE). Data in this report is allowed to be based on sample sizes of just 4. This means that a &amp;ldquo;study&amp;rdquo; could observe 4 total car trips and be included as bona fide evidence of exactly how much parking an entire city needs. If you have an understanding of statistics you should read the rest of the BTS&amp;rsquo;s analysis on this subject because the methodology is much worse than this tiny sample size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ITE presents 14 studies of trip generation at recreational land uses but says &amp;ldquo;No Plot or Equation AvailableInsufficient Data.&amp;rdquo; The trip generation rates in the 14 studies range from a high of 296 to a low of 0.066 trips per acre on a weekday: a ratio of 4,500 to 1. Given this wide range, reporting the average trip generation rate as precisely 3.635 trips per acre is clearly misleading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bts.gov/archive/publications/journal_of_transportation_and_statistics/volume_06_number_01/paper_01/index&#34;&gt;Truth in Transportation Planning&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; by Donald C. Shoup (Bureau of Transportation Statistics)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://urbanism.guide/media/ite_fast_food_trips.png&#34; alt=&#34;A chart showing the sparse and statistically unreliable data points used to determine average number of trips to fast food restaurants&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Institute of Transportation Engineers, Trip Generation, 4th edition (Washington, DC: 1987), p. 1,199. (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bts.gov/archive/publications/journal_of_transportation_and_statistics/volume_06_number_01/paper_01/figure_01_01&#34;&gt;via BTS&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end result being that there are now an estimated &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wsj.com/articles/parking-problem-too-much-cities-e94dcecf&#34;&gt;700 million to 2 billion parking spaces&lt;/a&gt; / (&lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.ph/BGpN3&#34;&gt;archive.ph mirror&lt;/a&gt;) per person in the US. We&amp;rsquo;ve built so much parking that nobody knows the true number. Put another way, at minimum, the US has between 2.1 and 6 parking spaces for every child under driving age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;parking-in-austin&#34;&gt;Parking in Austin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.axios.com/local/austin/2023/04/19/downtown-austin-parking&#34;&gt;17% of Downtown Austin is parking today&lt;/a&gt;. However the very good news is that parking mandates in Austin have recently been removed allowing for greater flexibility in how many parking spaces need to exist and allowing cities to reclaim parking spaces for human-centered, rather than car-centered uses. This, like many positive reforms, is due to the researchers, advocates, elected officials, city staff, and all those who worked to shed light on the parking issue our cities face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While 17% of a city&amp;rsquo;s downtown core is certainly a huge amount, Austin performs better than Houston, Dallas, and San Antonio where, according to Axios, 25% of their downtowns are dedicated to storing cars. The national average is 20%!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also worth keeping in mind that these rules do not eliminate parking, notably:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Residential and Commercial buildings can still build the parking they believe they need&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Federal standards around parking accessibility for people with disabilities will still be kept&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have a heck of a lot of parking already&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Austin&amp;rsquo;s Strategic Mobility Plan intends to have net no additional driving by 2039 by encouraging other forms of transportation for short distances&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-primary&#34; role=&#34;alert&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 class=&#34;alert-heading&#34;&gt;🚲&lt;/h4&gt;

    50% of trips in the US are 3 miles or less. As long as the infrastructure is there this is a quick 10 to 15 minute ride on an e-Bike or manual bike. Learn more about the benefits of biking, the city&amp;rsquo;s plans, and e-Bike discounts in our &lt;a href=&#34;https://urbanism.guide/austin/transportation/biking&#34;&gt;article on biking&lt;/a&gt;.

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;impacts-of-parking-mandates&#34;&gt;Impacts of Parking Mandates&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large &lt;a href=&#34;https://services.austintexas.gov/edims/document.cfm?id=417776&#34;&gt;added expense to housing costs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: According to Austin&amp;rsquo;s Housing &amp;amp; Planning department each parking spot in Austin adds $200/month to rent and $20,000-$60,000 per space in parking structures. These significant yet hidden costs add to displacement pressure in our cities, contributing to the further pricing out of people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creation of heat islands&lt;/strong&gt;: As anyone who&amp;rsquo;s had the displeasure of walking across a shopping mall during Texas&amp;rsquo; high heat can tell you, asphalt holds a lot of heat and can reach surface temperatures as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.usnews.com/news/world/articles/2023-07-31/how-concrete-asphalt-and-urban-heat-islands-add-to-the-misery-of-heat-waves&#34;&gt;high as 180 degrees&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/1352231094001405&#34;&gt;They then release this heat at night&lt;/a&gt;, creating summers that are perpetually hot no matter the hour.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- - **Impervious cover**: --&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It only takes just a fraction of a second to suffer a pretty serious burn. Asphalt and concrete in direct sunlight can often reach surface temperatures as high as 82 Celsius (180 Fahrenheit) on the hottest days, said Dr. Kevin Foster, who directs the Arizona Burn Center in Phoenix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; Dr. Kevin Foster, US News, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.usnews.com/news/world/articles/2023-07-31/how-concrete-asphalt-and-urban-heat-islands-add-to-the-misery-of-heat-waves&#34;&gt;How Concrete, Asphalt and Urban Heat Islands Add to the Misery of Heat Waves&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
